Yumeng HOU

yumeng.hou@epfl.ch | [Personal Page] | [Google Scholar] | [Web of Science] | [LinkedIn]

1. Biography

Yumeng Hou is a PhD candidate in digital humanities and computational (cultural) archives at EPFL, Switzerland. She earned her MSc in Computer Science from EPFL in 2017 and a BEng in Digital Media Technology from Zhejiang University in 2014. Yumeng has research and industrial experience in computational humanities, digital museology, data visualization, cultural analytics, intangible heritage, HCI, and cloud-based solutions, with a track record of publications, installations, and commercial projects.

2. Education	
PhD in Digital Humanities	Oct 2020 -
Doctoral School of Digital Humanities, EPFL, Switzerland	July 2024
Dissertation: "EncodingActs: Computational Curation of Embodied Knowledge Archives"	
Supervisor: Prof Sarah Kenderdine, Head of Laboratory for Experimental Museology and EPFL Pavilions	
MSc in Computer Science	2015 – 2017
School of Computer and Communication Sciences, EPFL, Switzerland	
GPA: 5.4/6 Thesis Project: "Visualizing Personal Nutrition Intake and Emotions", Supervisor: Dr Pearl Pu	
Semester Projects: "MOOC Clickstream Visual Analytics", Supervisor: Prof Pierre Dillenbourg and Dr Francisco	Pinto;
"APP Design and Development for a Smart Lunchbox", Supervisor: Prof Denis Gillet and Dr Marc Laperrouza	
BEng in Digital Media Technology	2010 – 2014

College of Computer Science and Technology, Zhejiang University, China

GPA: 3.8/4 | Thesis Project: "Visualizing Topic Evolutions in Wikipedia"; Supervisor: Prof Wei Chen

Exchange Student (Scholarship Recipient) 2010 - 2014

Department of Computer and Systems Sciences, Stockholm University, Sweden

GPA: A | Exchange Coordinator: Prof Preben Hansen

3. Research Experience

Doctoral Researcher	2020 – present
Laboratory for Experimental Museology, EPFL; Supervisor: Prof Sarah Kenderdine	
Visiting Scholar	July – Dec 2022
Visualization Research Centre (VRC), Hong Kong Baptist University; Supervisor: Prof Jeffrey Shaw	
Research Assistant	Jan – July 2017
Human-Computer Interaction Group, EPFL; Supervisor: Dr Pearl Pu	
Research Assistant	2013 – 2015
Visual Analytics and Intelligence Group, Zhejiang University; Supervisor: Prof Wei Chen	
4. Teaching and Supervising Experience	
Teaching Assistant & Lecturer & Project Mentor & Grader	2021 – 2023
 DH-404 Cultural Data Sculpting (21/22,22/23,23/24; 48 students), MSc in Digital Humanities, EPFL 	
Master's Semester Project Supervisor	
 12-credit project in Digital Humanities; Topic: Interactive interface 	Fall 2023/24
 12-credit project in Computer Science; Topic: Knowledge graph 	Spring 2021/22

 12-credit project in Digital Humanities; Topic: Interactive interface 	Fall 2023/24
 12-credit project in Computer Science; Topic: Knowledge graph 	Spring 2021/22
 10-credit project in Computation and Mathematics; Topic: Machine(/Deep) learning 	Fall 2021/22
Applied Project Mentor & Grader	

Applied Project Mentor & Grader

CS-433 Machine Learning, EPFL

EPFL's Doctoral School of Digital Humanities (EDDH)

Guest Lectures

•	"Computational Museology", in Digital Art History, University of Basel	Apr 8 2022
•	"Computational Motion Archives", in Cultural Data Sculpting, EPFL	Mar 31 2022
•	"Visualizing Embodied Knowledge Systems", in Cultural Data Sculpting, EPFL	May 20 2021

Invited Keynotes

 Keynote at Seminar on Digital Preservation of Cultural Heritage, Renmin University of China 	Jan 5 2024
 Keynote at The 4th International Martial Studies Conference, South China Normal University 	Nov 30 2022
Teaching Assistant (pre-PhD)	2014 – 2015

• Cross-Media Data Visualization (2014/2015), Zhejiang University

5. Academic Services

Peer Reviewer	2022 – present
Heritage Science, International Journal of Heritage Studies, Multimedia Tools and Applications, Digital	
Scholarship in the Humanities, Journal of Open Humanities Data, and Digital Humanities 2023	
PhD Student Representative, Doctoral School Committee Member	2021 – 2023

Conference/Seminar Organization

PhD Workshop on "Beyond Search: Opening Up Audiovisual Content for Humanities Studies"

Sep 25-26 2023

• PhD Seminar on "Human factors in Digital Humanities" (In addition to organizing and coordinating, I also handled fundraising, program design, lecturer invitation, PhD recruitment, and output editing.)

Dec 2-3 2021

Academic Memberships

- EuropeanaTech Communities & Research Communities, Europeana Network Association (2022 present)
- European Association for Digital Humanities (2023 present)
- Association for Computing Machinery (2021 present)
- Al4LAM Artificial Intelligence for Libraries, Archives & Museums (2021 present)
- UNIL-EPFL dhCenter (2020 present)

6. Grants and Awards

Europeana Network Association Member Grant (~6500): Travel bursary for attending EuropeanaTech 2023; Recipient.

EPFL Doc.Mobility Grant 2022 (~£12,000): A continuation of SNFS's instrument; Recipient & PI.

EPFL-UNIL CROSS Grant 2021-2022 (~66,000): Collaborative Research on Science and Society grant; Researcher.

Swissuniversities Support Program for Activities (~E8,000): As the EDDH student representative, I successfully applied to the program with the proposal for the PhD seminar on "Human factors in Digital Humanities"; **Applicant & Coordinator**.

Finalist for Best Paper Award at Digital Humanities 2023: a prize given for the best paper by an emerging scholar.

7. Publications

Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles

Hou, Y.* & Kenderdine, S. (2024). "Ontology-based Knowledge Representation for Traditional Martial Arts". *Digital Scholarship in the Humanities* (SSCI|AHCI). doi: 10.1093/llc/fqae005

Hou, Y.*, Seydou, F., & Kenderdine S. (2023). "Unlocking a multimodal archive of Southern Chinese martial arts through embodied cues". *Journal of Documentation* (SSCI). doi: 10.1108/JD-01-2022-0027

Hou, Y.* & Yuan, L. (2023) "Building a knowledge graph of Chinese kung fu masters from heterogeneous bilingual data". *Journal of Open Humanities Data* (DOAJ), Vol 9, No. 27. doi: 10.5334/johd.136

Hou, Y.*, Kenderdine S., et al. (2022). "Digitizing Intangible Cultural Heritage Embodied: state of the art". *Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage* (SCIE|AHCI), 15(3), pp.1-20. doi: 10.1145/3494837

Hou, Y.* (2021). "Accessing, Representing, and Transmitting Cultural Heritage through Digital Archives: challenges and opportunities". *Digital Humanities Research*, 4(1), 77-91. http://dhr.ruc.edu.cn/CN/Y2021/V1/I4/77

Alliata, G.*, **Hou, Y**. & Kenderdine, S. (2024). "Augmenting access to embodied knowledge archives: a computational framework". *Digital Humanities Quarterly* (ESCI). Just accepted.

Adamou, A.*, Picca, D., **Hou, Y.** & Granados-García, P. L. (2023). "The Facets of Intangible Heritage in Southern Chinese Martial Arts: Applying a Knowledge-Driven Cultural Contact Detection Approach". *Journal on Computing and Cultural Heritage* (SCIE|AHCI), 16(3), pp.1-27. doi: 10.1145/3606702

Xia, J., **Hou, Y.**, Chen, Y.V., Qian, Z.C., Ebert, D.S., & Chen, W.* (2017). "Visualizing rank time series of Wikipedia top-viewed pages". *IEEE computer graphics and applications* (SCIE), 37(2), 42-53. doi: 10.1109/MCG.2017.21

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings

Hou, Y. (2023). "Co-encoding embodied knowledge in Southern Chinese martial arts: a collaboration between computists, experts, and digital models". *Digital Humanities 2023: Book of Abstracts*. July 10-14 2023, Graz, Austria. doi: 10.5281/zenodo.8107443

Hou, Y.*, Kenderdine S. (2022). "Encoding the Whole-of-Environment Knowledge for Intangible Cultural Heritage". *AMPS Proceedings Series, 29.1 - (IN)TANGIBLE HERITAGE(S): Design, culture and technology – past, present, and future,* June 15-17, Canterbury, UK, pp.121-132.

Adamou, A.*, **Hou, Y.***, Picca, D.*, et al. (2021). "Ontology-mediated cultural contact in Southern Chinese martial arts". *Proceedings of the International Joint Workshop on Semantic Web and Ontology Design for Cultural Heritage*. https://ceurws.org/Vol-2949/short2.pdf

Picca, D.*, Adamou, A.*, **Hou, Y.**, et al. (2022). "Knowledge organization of the Hong Kong Martial Arts Living Archive to capture and preserve intangible cultural heritage". *Digital Humanities 2022*. July 25-29 2022, Tokyo.

Xia, J., Chen, W.*, **Hou, Y.**, et al. (2016). "Dimscanner: A relation-based visual exploration approach towards data dimension inspection". In *Proceedings of 2016 IEEE Conference on Visual Analytics Science and Technology* (VAST), pp. 81-90. IEEE. <u>doi: 10.1109/VAST.2016.7883514</u>

Contributions to Books

Kenderdine, S.*, Hibberd, L., Shaw, J., Chang, T.Z., & **Hou, Y**. (2023). "Archery Rites: Re-making Confucian Rites". *Chinese Archery Studies: Theoretical and Historical Approaches to a Martial Discipline*. Springer. doi: 10.1007/978-981-16-8321-3 13

Hou, Y. (2024). "Reliving martial arts classics in the digital era". Dushu Magazine, issue 10, Joint Publishing (H.K.). [preview]

Edited Volume

Hou, Y. (Ed.). (2021). Proceedings of the EPFL PhD Seminar "Human factors in Digital Humanities". EPFL Infoscience.

8. Oral Contributions to Conferences: Presentations, Posters, and Talks

"Reimagining Cultural Archive Access and Engagement in the Digital Age". Presentation at the *International Symposium on Transformations in Museums through Digital Initiatives*, Jan 12-13 2024, UMAG The University of Hong Kong.

"Building and Disrupting the Hong Kong Martial Arts Living Archive: from digital to computational". Invited talk at the Seminar on Digital Preservation of Cultural Heritage, Jan 5 2024, Renmin University of China, Beijing.

"The (in)accessible embodiment: Unfolding the multifaceted knowledge in traditional martial arts". Paper presentation at *EuropeanaTech 2023*, Oct 11-12 2023, Den Haag, Netherlands.

"Datafication: Towards Digital Transmission of the Living Heritage of Southern Chinese Martial Arts". Paper presentation at *The 9th Young Scholars' Forum in Chinese Studies 2023*, Sept 7-8 2023, Hong Kong.

Research presentation at the Post-CHI Summer School on Extended Reality (XR), May 2-4 2023, Copenhagen.

"Computational Archives and Museology+", in Expert Lecture Series, _box Interaction Studio, Dec 5 2022, Hangzhou.

"Towards Digital Preservation of Traditional Chinese Martial Arts". Keynote speech at *The 4th International Martial Studies Conference*, Nov 30 2022, Guangzhou, China.

"Augmenting Knowledge Exploration Using Agent-Based Models: A computational experiment with the HKMALA". Paper presentation at the 7th International Martial Arts Studies Conference. June 29 - July 2 2022, Lausanne, Switzerland.

"Artificial Intelligence for Cultural Heritage and Computational Archives". Guest lecture in *Digital Art History: Current Trends and Experimental Applications*, University of Basel, April 8 2022.

"Computational Motion Archives", Guest lecture in Cultural Data Sculpting, EPFL, 31 March 2022.

"Motion as Meaning: Representing embodied knowledge in multimodal cultural archives". Speech at *DHCH@ISR 2021*, June 7-9 2021, Rome, Italy.

"Visualizing Embodied Knowledge Systems", Guest lecture in Cultural Data Sculpting, EPFL, 20 May 2021.

"Articulate Similarity: A Visual Search Framework for Embodied Knowledge in A Confucian Rites Video Archive". Poster at 16th International Digital Curation Conference (IDCC21), April 19 2021, Online.

"Dimscanner: A relation-based visual exploration approach towards data dimension inspection". Paper presentation at the *IEEE Conference on Visual Analytics Science and Technology* (VAST), 23-28 October 2016.

"Visualizing and Understanding Ranking Trends of Wikipedia Top Viewed Pages". Poster at PacificVis 2015, 14-17 April 2015.

"Visual Data Inspection". Poster at PacificVis 2015, 14-17 April 2015.

9. Professional Experience (Industry)

Creative Tech Lead	2019 – 2020
_box Interaction, Hangzhou, China	
Digital Strategist (part-time)	2019 – 2020
NewStyle Media Group, Beijing/Hangzhou, China	
Technical Product Manager – Media Cloud Service PaaS, SaaS and SDK	2017 – 2019
Alibaba Cloud, Hangzhou, China	
Digital Consumer Analyst EMEA (internship)	2016 – 2017
Procter & Gamble, Geneva, Switzerland	
Lead Software Engineer & APP Designer (part-time)	2015 – 2018
HIBACHI (IoT x Entrepreneurship), Lausanne, Switzerland	

10. Additional Exhibitions, Installations, and Creative Works

Museum of Poetry Cultural Experience @Keqiao. Co-curator. A digital, playful, and interactive museum. [demo] ImmerScience. Tech lead. An immersive learning space created for Daning International School, Shanghai. [demo] Natural Origins of The Internet. Artist. Data Art Installation. Museum of Inspiration, Hangzhou. [repo] Mirrori. Designer. A design for the augmented era, transmitting exhibition experience to a 2D interface. [blog] AquA. Designer. A virtual aquarium motivating knowledge sharing. Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF), Geneva. [repo] MOOC Learning Flow. Designer & Developer. A visualization of learners' path with outcome prediction. [repo] SPARK. Designer. An interactive stress management APP designed during the HCI course, EPFL. [demo]

11. Language and Skills

Language: Mandarin (native), English (proficient), French (intermediate, B1/B2), Cantonese (elementary).

Knowledge Fields: Cultural Heritage, Digital Archives, Semantic Web, Machine Learning, User Experience (UX), Data Visualization, Visual Analytics, VR/AR/XR, Digital/Virtual Museum, Motion Capture, Cloud Solution, HCI

Programming: Python, JavaScript (D3.js, three.js, p5.js), SQL/Cypher, R, Java, processing, HTML/CSS, C++, etc.

Tools: UE4, Unity, Axure, Media Processing (DaVinci, Photoshop, Audition, AI, etc), Neo4j, Knime, MS Office, etc.

Soft Skills: Product Design and Management, Communication, Data-driven Mindset, Agile, Team Spirit, Empathy

Others: Chinese Martial Arts, Musical Keyboard, Jazz Drumming, Yoga

[&]quot;A Visual Analysis System for Event Detection from Network Log Data". Presentation at IEEE VAST Challenge 2013.